so let's practice calculating
equilibrium concentrations
consider the following equilibrium with
N2 + 3H2 in equilibrium with 2NH3
now at equilibrium the nitrogen
concentration is 4 point 2 6 molar the
hydrogen concentration is 2 point zero 9
molar and the equilibrium constant for
this system is zero point zero six zero
zero what is the equilibrium
concentration of NH3? so if this seems
confusing check out my tutorial on
equilibria and then give this a try.
so this is a very straightforward situation
here is our equilibrium now the first
thing we want to do is generate our
equilibrium constant expression now
recall that will involve placing the
concentrations of the products over the
concentrations of the reactants and then
the concentrations are going to be
raised to the power of the relevant
stoichiometric coefficient so whatever
the coefficient is on a substance the
concentration of that substance will be
raised to that power so in this case we
have our equilibrium constant being
equal to the concentration of ammonia
squared because ammonia has a
coefficient of 2 over the concentration
of nitrogen times the concentration of
hydrogen raised to the 3rd power because
hydrogen has a coefficient of 3 so that
is our expression and now we just plug
in what we know and as it turns out we
know everything except one thing so we
have that constant it is zero point zero
six zero zero we have our nitrogen
concentration it's four point two six
and we have our hydrogen concentration
it's two point zero nine
and that will be raised to the third
power so here all we have to do is a
little bit of arithmetic and we get the
ammonia concentration squared as being
equal to two point three three and then
we take the square root and our answer
will be one point five three molar.